<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://domsav13.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://domsav13.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2026-01-10T02:47:11+00:00</updated><id>https://domsav13.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Building deep neural networks from scratch</title><link href="https://domsav13.github.io/blog/2025/mnist/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Building deep neural networks from scratch"/><published>2025-12-18T15:12:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-12-18T15:12:00+00:00</updated><id>https://domsav13.github.io/blog/2025/mnist</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://domsav13.github.io/blog/2025/mnist/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Training of neural networks on the MNIST dataset]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Controls for a 2D rocket</title><link href="https://domsav13.github.io/blog/2025/2drocket/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Controls for a 2D rocket"/><published>2025-12-10T15:12:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-12-10T15:12:00+00:00</updated><id>https://domsav13.github.io/blog/2025/2drocket</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://domsav13.github.io/blog/2025/2drocket/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[LQG and model predictive control of a rocket for hovering, landing, and waypoint flight]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Prosthetic leg</title><link href="https://domsav13.github.io/blog/2025/prosthesis/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Prosthetic leg"/><published>2025-12-08T15:12:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-12-08T15:12:00+00:00</updated><id>https://domsav13.github.io/blog/2025/prosthesis</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://domsav13.github.io/blog/2025/prosthesis/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Requirement analysis and design of a knee prosthesis]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Nonlinear control of a DC motor</title><link href="https://domsav13.github.io/blog/2025/nonlinear-controls/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Nonlinear control of a DC motor"/><published>2025-11-25T15:12:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-11-25T15:12:00+00:00</updated><id>https://domsav13.github.io/blog/2025/nonlinear-controls</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://domsav13.github.io/blog/2025/nonlinear-controls/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Control system design using Lyapunov stability and sliding manifolds]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Basic and optimal control of a double pendulum</title><link href="https://domsav13.github.io/blog/2025/pendulum/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Basic and optimal control of a double pendulum"/><published>2025-10-14T15:12:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-10-14T15:12:00+00:00</updated><id>https://domsav13.github.io/blog/2025/pendulum</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://domsav13.github.io/blog/2025/pendulum/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Control system design using pole placement, linear quadratic regulator, and Kalman filter]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">System identification of a DC motor</title><link href="https://domsav13.github.io/blog/2025/sys-id/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="System identification of a DC motor"/><published>2025-09-10T15:12:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-09-10T15:12:00+00:00</updated><id>https://domsav13.github.io/blog/2025/sys-id</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://domsav13.github.io/blog/2025/sys-id/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[White- and black-box approaches to motor control]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">MAE Senior Capstone</title><link href="https://domsav13.github.io/blog/2025/capstone/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="MAE Senior Capstone"/><published>2025-05-10T15:12:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-10T15:12:00+00:00</updated><id>https://domsav13.github.io/blog/2025/capstone</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://domsav13.github.io/blog/2025/capstone/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Design and build of a maritime spotlight]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">IoT Christmas Tree</title><link href="https://domsav13.github.io/blog/2025/xmas-tree/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="IoT Christmas Tree"/><published>2025-05-10T15:12:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-10T15:12:00+00:00</updated><id>https://domsav13.github.io/blog/2025/xmas-tree</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://domsav13.github.io/blog/2025/xmas-tree/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Coordinate- and sensor-based Christmas tree lighting]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Object tracking and identification</title><link href="https://domsav13.github.io/blog/2025/opencv/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Object tracking and identification"/><published>2025-03-10T15:12:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-10T15:12:00+00:00</updated><id>https://domsav13.github.io/blog/2025/opencv</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://domsav13.github.io/blog/2025/opencv/"><![CDATA[<p>This project explores computer vision-based object detection and facial recognition using a Raspberry Pi 4B and PiCamera V2.1 to create a compact, real-time security/detection system. The detection model captures video frames, processes them in real time, and sends notifications when a target is detected. OpenCV, a widely used computer vision library, and the COCO dataset were used to develop and train the model. The object detection performed reliably with adjustable confidence thresholds, but facial recognition struggled with prolonged use due to hardware limitations.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="background">Background</h3> <p>Using a three-layer IoT model incorporating the perception, network, and application layers, the final product seeks to generate email notifications based on visual detection methods. The work is inspired by security and privacy computer vision-based systems (Ring, Apple Face ID, etc.).</p> <p>OpenCV is a free computer vision and machine learning library built to advance machine perception in commercial products, featuring thousands of optimized algorithms that can be used to detect and recognize faces, identify objects, classify gestures, and more. The fundamentals of object detection in OpenCV involve two main tasks: classification and localization. Most methods work to determine the exact location of an object within an image or video feed by using bounding boxes or segmentation. The promises of OpenCV rely fully on the models that are provided, which is why the Common Objects in Context (COCO) dataset is essential for the success of the detection performance.</p> <p>COCO is a large-scale object detection dataset that features recognition of over 200,000 labeled images among 1.5 million object instances. The datasets are open source and available for download, and are designed to train and evaluate detection models with rich contextual data and precise localization via “segmentation masks,” a specific portion of an image that is isolated from the rest. This project will use OpenCV algorithms to train these labeled images so that a Raspberry Pi and PiCamera can detect objects and alert the user in real time.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="methods-and-implementation">Methods and implementation</h3> <p>The requirements for this project include a Raspberry Pi 4 (flashed with the Buster version of the Debian OS) and PiCamera V2.1. The camera interfaces with the microcomputer with a ribbon connector.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-12 col-md-5 mx-auto mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/eyepi-workflow-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/eyepi-workflow-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/eyepi-workflow-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/eyepi-workflow.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Software workflow for the email notification and object detection system. </div> <p>The primary goal of the code is to detect a specific object, capture an image when the object is detected, and send an email with the image attached. The pre-trained COCO dataset incorporates the labeling of 91 common everyday objects. The object detection model is configured using these COCO files to define class labels and specify weights, which is later loaded by the OpenCV deep neural network module. A video capture continuously reads frames and passes them through a function that checks whether the detected object matches the target object specified by the user. If so, it draws a bounding box and a label around the object on the image, saves it, and sends it via email. This function is central to the object detection process, as it uses a confidence and non-maximum suppression (NMS) threshold. The confidence threshold filters out low-confidence detections and the NMS thresholds reduces overlapping boxes to avoid duplicate detections. The email is sent using SMTP, EmailMessage, and a Gmail account with app passwords enabled to include a subject and body message indicating that the object was detected, attaching the saved image as well.</p> <p>All code is presented at <a href="https://github.com/domsav13/eyepi">this GitHub repo</a>.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="results">Results</h3> <p>Overall, the methods satisfied basic requirements but were limited due to hardware constraints. The limited computing power of the Raspberry Pi and low frame rates in the video feed limited the performance of the software, however the object detection model met expectations.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-12"> <div class="row justify-content-center"> <div class="col-12 col-md-6"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/detection-left-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/detection-left-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/detection-left-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/detection-left.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-12 col-md-6"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/detection-right-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/detection-right-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/detection-right-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/detection-right.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Exclusive search within the video feed, filtering out specified objects. Bounding boxes and confidence levels are shown around each object. Left: objects=[""]; Right: objects=["CUP"]. </div> <p>There are a few hyperparameters that the user can modify. First, using an exclusive search feature of OpenCV, the user may specify which object or group of objects the detection model should look for. In other words, the user can filter out undesired objects from the detection model if only searching for instances of objects of interest. Additionally, the user may choose the confidence threshold for the detection. While objects such as cups, chairs, or people are easily detectable, there are fewer common objects that require lower confidence thresholds. A high confidence level is typically above 0.7 whereas a poor confidence is below 0.4.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-12"> <div class="row justify-content-center"> <div class="col-12 col-md-6"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/broccoli-detected-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/broccoli-detected-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/broccoli-detected-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/broccoli-detected.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-12 col-md-6"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/chair-detected-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/chair-detected-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/chair-detected-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/chair-detected.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> The COCO dataset used here contains 91 everyday objects, but not all are detected with high confidence by the OpenCV model. The difficulty is reflected in the confidence metric that is displayed with each bounding box. </div> <p>Lastly, the implementation of a personal security system that detects people and sends email alerts to the home user (inspired by Ring) works exceptionally well due to the high confidence of “person” in the detection model and simple, rapid communication via WiFi. Not only does the email notification include a snapshot of the detected object, it also provides a timestamp and a description of which object was detected.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-12 col-md-5 mx-auto mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/eyepi-email-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/eyepi-email-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/eyepi-email-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/eyepi-email.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Sample email notification with detection timestamp and "person" as the target object, sent by a third-party email account. </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Pocket-sized computer vision (OpenCV)]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mini foosball table</title><link href="https://domsav13.github.io/blog/2024/foosball/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mini foosball table"/><published>2024-11-25T15:12:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-25T15:12:00+00:00</updated><id>https://domsav13.github.io/blog/2024/foosball</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://domsav13.github.io/blog/2024/foosball/"><![CDATA[<p>The goals of this manufacturing project were to define product specifications using CAD software, outline component requirements by developing manufacturing process plans, gain experience with simple machine shop machines (lathe, mill, drill press, etc.), manage internal and external resources, and build and test the final design.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/foosball-1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/foosball-1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/foosball-1-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/foosball-1.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/foosball-2-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/foosball-2-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/foosball-2-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/foosball-2.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Final product of the mini foosball table. </div> <p>The project also highlights the important differences between design for manufacturability (DFM) and design for assembly (DFA). DFM focuses on making individual parts easy and cost-effective to manufacture while DFA focuses on minimizing the time, cost, and errors involved in assembling those parts into a finished product. There are several tradeoffs that were observed between DFM and DFA, trying to bring a CAD model to life, and through understanding the practical capabilities of the available machines.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="design">Design</h3> <p>Each component was designed and modeled in SOLIDWORKS to visualize a baseline assembly. This version featured 10 player models and had dimensions 12.5 x 19.75 inches.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-12"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/foosball-assembly-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/foosball-assembly-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/foosball-assembly-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/foosball-assembly.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> The initial CAD assembly for the mini foosball table, showing the original key components: base, goal walls, side walls, player, and rod. </div> <p>This assembly was helpful in streamlining the manufacturing process plans for the key components, but it is not representative of the final product for several reasons. During the manufacturing phase, back walls were designed and manufactured to create a space to collect the ball once a goal has been scored; bushings were selected to allow near-frictionless movement of the rods through the through holes in the side walls; player heads were 3D printed in two different colors to distinguish between teams; handles were manufactured and attached to the rods for comfortable control of players; and bumpers were added to rods with 2 players to prevent unwanted contact with the side walls.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="manufacturing-and-assembly">Manufacturing and assembly</h3> <p>A wide variety of machines were used in the manufacturing processes, including the lathe, mill, band and drop saws, and drill press. The saws were primarily used to make preliminary cuts in the raw material for each component. The drill press was used to make through holes in the side walls and the player bases. The lathe was used to turn down the players (machined using stock Aluminum) into equal sizes and was then programmed to do a revolve cut to achieve a geometry similar to a standard foosball player model. A similar approach was used to turn down the ends of the handles to make them hemispherical in shape. The lathe was further used to drill center holes in the tops of the players (for assembly with the 3D printed heads) and the handles (for assembly with the rods).</p> <swiper-container class="media-swiper" keyboard="true" navigation="true" pagination="true" pagination-clickable="true" pagination-dynamic-bullets="true" rewind="true"> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/player-sketch-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/player-sketch-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/player-sketch-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/player-sketch.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/player-lathe-cutting-path-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/player-lathe-cutting-path-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/player-lathe-cutting-path-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/player-lathe-cutting-path.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> <swiper-slide> <figure> <video src="/assets/img/lathe_player.mp4" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" controls=""/> </figure> </swiper-slide> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/lathe-drilling-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/lathe-drilling-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/lathe-drilling-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/lathe-drilling.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> </swiper-container> <p>The mill was then used to flatten a bottom section on the player models to create an optimal contact surface with the game ball. It was also used to create the goal cavity in the goal walls, as well as ensure that all walls are of equal height.</p> <swiper-container class="media-swiper" keyboard="true" navigation="true" pagination="true" pagination-clickable="true" pagination-dynamic-bullets="true" rewind="true"> <swiper-slide> <figure> <video src="/assets/img/mill_player.mp4" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" controls=""/> </figure> </swiper-slide> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/foosball-walls-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/foosball-walls-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/foosball-walls-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/foosball-walls.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> <swiper-slide> <figure> <video src="/assets/img/mill_goal.mp4" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" controls=""/> </figure> </swiper-slide> </swiper-container> <p>Of all machined components, the part that differs the most from the original concept is the player base, due to the complexity of the first iteration. The finalized geometry reflects a simpler design based on the amount of time available to complete the machining and the resources and machines available. Because of how each individual component meticulously interfaces, system-level assembly was especially important. Precision was emphasized as the assembly phase began, where threaded inserts were carefully installed to ensure the walls, base, and player rods connected as desired. Bushings were ordered from McMaster-Carr so that the rods could translate with little friction in the side walls.</p> <swiper-container class="media-swiper" keyboard="true" navigation="true" pagination="true" pagination-clickable="true" pagination-dynamic-bullets="true" rewind="true"> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/wall-player-assembly-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/wall-player-assembly-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/wall-player-assembly-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/wall-player-assembly.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/wall-bushings-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/wall-bushings-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/wall-bushings-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/wall-bushings.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/final-assembly-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/final-assembly-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/final-assembly-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/final-assembly.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> </swiper-container> <p>For the most part, the mini foosball table functions as desired. However, due to the changes in the player model geometries from CAD to real life, there is slight unwanted contact that occurs between players of consecutive rods, which can significantly affect performance.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Design, manufacturing, and assembly of a scaled-down foosball table]]></summary></entry></feed>